So here we are now, back in the Colab, in the same one that we kicked off in the previous day.
다시 콜랍으로 돌아왔어요 어제 시작한 바로 그 장소죠
It's now somewhat misleadingly named week seven, day three because we are of course on week seven,
지금은 7주 차나 3일째라고 잘못 명명됐어요 7주 차나 4일째에 찍었거든요
But I daren't touch it for fear that I that I, uh, stop it in some way.
하지만 만질 수가 없어요 제가 어떤 식으로든 막을 수 있을까 봐서요
You can see that the GPU Ram continues in its nail, bitingly close to the ceiling level of 38.2 out
GPU 램이 계속 천장 레벨 38에 근접하게 유지되고 있네요 40GB에서 2개요
But it's luckily not changing.
다행히도 바뀌지 않네요
Not going up.
안 올라가요
And you'll see here this is the printout of each of the different batch steps as they happen.
여기 출력된 게 보이시죠 각각의 배치 단계가 발생하는 대로요
We're now on batch step 4350.
지금은 4350단계예요
Um, and if we zoom all the way up, uh, which again, I'm doing everything very delicately so I don't
줌인해서 끝까지 올리면... 다시 말하지만 아주 섬세하게 작업하고 있어요 실수로 반죽이
accidentally stop the batch in some way.
멈추는 일이 없도록요
You can see that we're only a little tiny way into this strip that represents all three epochs.
세 개 시대의 모습을 볼 수 있는 아주 작은 구역이에요
So one about there perhaps is a complete, uh, run through all of the data.
여기 있는 것 중 하나는 모든 데이터를 훑는 거죠
Um, and you can see we're at batch step.
보다시피 배치 스텝이에요
Uh, I can't say the number because it's ticking too fast, but for for ten, uh, there we go.
너무 빨리 가서 숫자는 말 못 하지만 10달러면... 좋아요
Uh, out of this very round number, uh, that you see here of 100,000, uh, and you might wonder why
여기 보이는 100,000라는 둥근 숫자에서 왜 이렇게 둥근지 궁금하실
it's quite so round.
거예요
Uh, and, uh, it's just something of a coincidence.
그냥 우연의 일치예요
Uh, remember, we have 400,000 data points, and but they're in batches of 16 are in any one step.
데이터 포인트가 400,000개인데 16개씩 묶어서 한 단계에 있어요
So if I take my calculator here for this trivial maths, take 400 000 and I divide that by 16.
이 하찮은 수학 계산기에 대해 계산을 해보죠 40만 달러를 16으로 나누죠
Uh, and then I multiply that by the number of epochs.
그걸 여러 시대의 개수로 곱한 거예요.
Um, I thought we had three epochs, but it looks like we have four epochs.
세 개 개국인 줄 알았는데 네 개국인 것 같네요
I left it at four epochs.
네 개국에서 활동했죠
Uh, so, uh, yeah.
그래서 네
If you then multiply that by four for four epochs.
네 개의 개화에 4를 곱하면
Uh, you do end up with, uh, just to give evidence of that, there's the camera, uh, 100,000, uh,
결국 증거를 남기게 되죠 여기 카메라가 있네요 100,000번 카메라예요 이게 100,000번
and it's that that is the 100,000 here.
카메라죠
It's not just a wild random number, randomly round number.
무작위로 나온 숫자가 아니에요
It is, in fact, exactly the number of batch steps involved in 400,000 data points, grouped into batches
정확히 400,000개의 데이터 포인트에 관련된 배치 단계의 수입니다 16개의
of 16, done four times over.
배치로 묶였고 4번 이상 이루어졌죠
Uh, so off it ticks.
틱틱거리는 거죠
And you can see just from looking at these numbers that we started with quite high training loss and
이 수치만 봐도 알 수 있어요 훈련에서 손실이 컸을 때 시작했는데
that that number has come down, uh, quite significantly.
그 손실이 눈에 띄게 줄었어요
But it's sort of hard to tell from here exactly what's going on, because the numbers bounce around
하지만 이 화면만 봐서는 정확히 알 수 없어요 수치가 위아래로 흔들리거든요
Um, and it's hard to get a sense of the trend.
Get it 유행도 파악하기 어렵고요
If only there were a tool that would allow us to visualize the progress of the batch in a way that could
배치의 진행을 시각화할 수 있는 툴이 있다면 좋을 텐데요 실행과 비슷한 것을
allow us to compare between different runs and the like.
비교할 수 있는 툴이요
Of course, there is such a tool and it's weights and biases and it's sitting right here.
무게와 편향성이라는 도구가 바로 여기 있어요
Um, and this this is the result of our run.
이게 그 결과물이에요
This is it happening right now.
지금 벌어지고 있어요
Um, and this is showing us what's going on.
무슨 일이 일어나는지 보여주는 거예요
So.
그래서요?
So this training loss here is the real the real thing.
이 훈련의 손실은 실전이에요
This is what we really want to look at.
우리가 정말 보고 싶은 건 이거예요
Let me just edit this panel so we get to see it a bit more.
이 패널을 수정해서 좀 더 보도록 하죠 get it get it
Um, now this the the y axis here goes all the way down to zero where zero will be zero loss, which
여기 있는 y축은 끝까지 0까지 이어지는데 0은 손실이 0이 되니 완벽을
would mean perfection.
의미하죠
It would mean that the model is always predicting with 100% confidence the next token and that next
이 모델은 항상 100% 확신으로 다음 토큰을 예측하고 100% 확신으로 예측한
token that it predicts with 100% confidence is the right next token.
다음 토큰이 올바른 다음 토큰이 되는 거죠
Um, so that is an unlikely place to get.
get it up
In fact, one would be suspicious if you got much below 1.5.
1점보다 낮으면 의심받을 만하죠 5분
Typically this is a bit of a rule of thumb thing, but but generally speaking, that would be like a
보통은 경험에서 우러나오는 비법이지만 일반적으로
great, uh, loss to have.
보면 큰 손실이에요
And below that might cause you pause for thought about whether overfitting is going on.
그 아래로는 너무 많이 끼는 건 아닌지 생각할 시간이 생기죠
Um, let me change these axes and make the minimum of the y axis one so that.
이 축을 바꿔서 y 축을 최소화할게요
Well, we can make it.
갈 수 있어요
We can do even better.
더 잘할 수 있어요
We can make it like 1.4 or something, um, so that we can really see what's going on here.
1로 하죠 4시쯤에 보면 어떤지 알 수 있을 거예요
Um, and it's a bumpy line, but it is pretty clear even at this early stage, that that is a bumpy
울퉁불퉁한 코스지만 초반 단계에서도 분명한 건 울퉁불퉁한 코스지만 발전하는
line that has an improving trend.
추세가 있다는 거예요
Unlike when we saw this with, uh, GPT and the fine tuning, when it seemed to be bouncing up and down
GPT와 미세 조율로 봤을 때와는 달리 위아래로 흔들리기만 하고 별다른
but not really showing a trend, I think you can see that this looks like it's improving.
변화는 없었는데 지금은 나아지고 있는 것 같아요
We can also apply the smoothing thing and see how that looks.
표면을 매끄럽게 하는 것도 가능해요
I mean, that's clearly isn't it.
이건 확실히 아니에요
That is that is a line that is improving.
그 선이 나아지고 있어요
If we apply the smoothing factor.
부드러움을 더하면요
Now, why do these bump up and down?
왜 위아래로 흔들릴까요?
I mean it depends really.
상황에 따라 다르죠
It's remember each of these points represents, uh, 16 data points, 16 prompts with a thing for it
각각의 점들은 16개의 데이터 포인트와 16개의 프롬프트입니다. 하나의 끝부분에
to predict at the end of it shoved into one and it's a random it's been jumbled up.
있는 예측할 수 있는 것들이죠. 무작위로 뒤섞여 있어요.
So it's a random set of the 16.
16개의 무작위 세트예요
And so who knows which products are shoved into the 16.
16번 테이블에 어떤 제품을 넣었는지 누가 알겠어요?
There could be some really expensive products that it's making a wild guess at and getting completely
정말 비싼 제품이 있을 수도 있어요 그냥 추측만 하고 완전히 틀린 제품요
wrong.
그래서 소음이 많죠
Um, because the there's a different makeup of each of these different batch steps, and it's good to
각 단계마다 구성이 다르기 때문에 비트를 좀 섞는 게
have a bit of noise because you want to be shaking things up a bit and getting the model to be, um,
좋아요 그래야 흔들리는 느낌이 나거든요 모델이 이리저리 흔들리는
being bounced around.
느낌요
Um, in a sense, again, I'm being very hand-wavy, but because you're trying to not get stuck in a
어떤 면에서는 수작업으로 하고 있어요 최소한의 지역에만
local minimum, but be trying out different, different possibilities with the idea that the model will
머물러 있지 않고 다양한 가능성을 시도해야 하니까요 모델이
improve and find a big global minimum, a big valley as it tries to, to, um, find gradients and improve
개선될 수 있도록요 글로벌 최소의 큰 계곡을 찾으면서 그러데이션을 찾고 다음 토큰을 예측하는
its ability to predict the next token.
능력을 향상시키죠
Um, it's just moved on a little bit.
비트가 조금 바뀌었어요
And again, it's very clear that there is visually some improvement happening here.
다시 말하지만 시각적으로 개선된 점이 분명히 보이네요
Um, so what else can we see?
또 뭐가 있을까요?
So this is the learning rate.
이게 학습률이군요
This is the, uh, the that key hyperparameter about how much of a step it should take.
이게 그 키 하이퍼파라미터예요 얼마나 걸어야 하는지 알 수 있죠
And I told you we'd chosen a cosine learning rate, and you might be a bit surprised to see something
코사인 학습 비트를 정했다고 말씀드렸는데 놀라실지도 모르겠네요
which doesn't look very cosine y at all and doesn't look the way I described it.
전혀 코사인 같지 않고 제가 설명한 것과도 달라요
And this what you're seeing here is that thing called warm up, which is the fact that it that it doesn't
지금 보시는 건 워밍업이라는 건데요 0에서
start up at the, the 0.0001, the highest number, it starts at zero and builds up to that point.
시작하지 않는다는 거죠 가장 높은 숫자 0001은 0에서 시작해서 0까지 쌓이죠
Because you can see the beginning of the batch is quite a dramatic movement from being way off to to
반죽이 시작될 때 극적으로 움직이잖아요 멀리 있다가 더 좋은 위치로
being in a better position.
이동하죠
And you don't want the learning rate to be too high then.
학습률이 너무 높으면 안 되죠
Or it might do, it might overshoot in all sorts of ways.
아니면 모든 면에서 지나칠 수도 있고요
So that's the theory behind this warm up.
그게 이 준비 운동의 원리예요
Um, uh, part of the process.
과정의 일부죠
Um, and you can see it really, really coming to, to, to be here.
실제로 이 자리에 서게 될 거예요
Um, and you might wonder why this isn't really showing much in the way of a cosine kind of, uh, shape.
왜 코사인 형태가 안 보이는지 궁금하실 거예요
And that's because it's so early in the training.
훈련 초반이라 그래요
Still, we're still at the very top of this cosine.
그래도 코사인 꼭대기에 있어요
It's about to start curving down, and it's doing that very slowly.
아래로 구부러지기 시작하는데 아주 천천히 구부러져요
Um, and, um, yeah, there's also some fun charts here that show us what's going on on the GPU.
GPU 상황에 대해 보여주는 재미있는 차트도 있어요
Uh, some of these are more meaningful than others.
어떤 건 다른 것보다 더 의미가 있어요
There's some here.
여기 있어요
The, um.
그거요
Yeah, the power usage and the time spent accessing memory is good.
전력 사용량과 메모리 접근 시간은 좋아요
Uh, it's.
네
I want to see the CPU utilization.
CPU 활용도를 보고 싶어요
Where is that?
그게 어디죠?
I mean, the GPU, even the CPU utilization.
GPU CPU 활용도까지도요
The GPU utilization would be the perhaps one of the most important to make sure that the time that the
GPU 활용도는 GPU가 열심히 일하는 시간을 확인하는 데 가장 중요한 부분일 겁니다
GPU is hard at work, it's not like it's shepherding memory in and out, and that that's what's taking
메모리를 안팎으로 처리하는 데 시간이 걸리는 게 아니죠
You want to know that the GPU is being utilized.
GPU 사용 여부를 알고 싶은 거죠
And that's a great sign that we are hammering our are powerful A100 blocks and making the most out of
강력한 A100 블록을 망치질하며 최대한 활용하고 있다는 신호죠
it.
다른 상자를 사용한다면 다른 hyperpaameter가 생기죠
Then come and check out the GPU utilization, make sure it's doing well, make sure it's nice and hot,
GPU 활용도를 확인하세요 잘 작동하는지 잘 작동하는지
uh, and that you're getting good use out of your GPU.
GPU를 잘 활용하고 있는지 확인하세요
Otherwise, you might want to tweak some of the hyperparameters to see if you can't get more juice out
하이퍼파라미터 일부를 수정해 get을 더 끌어낼 수 있는지
of it so that it's your training process is more efficient.
볼 수도 있어요 훈련 과정이 더 효율적이게요
Um, okay.
네
So what I'm going to do now is do a bit of a cheat.
이제 비트를 좀 쓸 거예요
I'm going to do what they do in those cooking classes or like, like cooking videos when they put it
요리 수업이나 오븐에 넣는 영상에서 배웠던 걸 해볼게요
in the oven and they say, and now here's one that I did earlier, they take it out of the oven and
아까 했던 걸 보여드릴게요 오븐에서 꺼낸 걸
it's the thing that they put in, you know, it's like, oh, that's uh, that's just cheating.
그대로 넣는 건 속임수라고들 하잖아요
But I have done that and that I did kick this off a while back and it ran with the same hyperparameters.
하지만 전 그걸 했고 얼마 전에 이걸 시작했었죠 동일 hyperperameter로 실행됐어요
So the same thing, um, and, uh, and it's this pink one right here.
같은 거예요 여기 분홍색요
And this I should have explained.
제가 설명을 못 드렸네요
I'm so sorry.
정말 미안해요
This here is showing the four runs that have happened under this project.
이 프로젝트에서 실행된 4개의 실행을 보여주고 있어요
The project which is called Pricer.
프라이서라는 프로젝트죠
So up at the top here, this navigation, um, it has the Pricer project.
상단에 있는 내비게이션에는 프라이서 프로젝트가 있어요
And down here are the four runs.
여기 네 번의 경주가 있는데요
Um, and this run here was when I ran either 3 or 4 epochs, um, of this model with this same data
이것은 제가 서너 개의 이포크를 실행했을 때 같은 데이터셋으로
set and with the, uh, yeah.
실행한 것인데요
With otherwise with everything else the same.
다른 건 다 똑같아요
Uh, and so if I show you that, we'll see what happened as a result of that.
그걸 보여드리면 그 결과 어떻게 됐는지 알 수 있죠
And here we go.
자, 보세요
So this this is, uh, this is the meaty one.
이게 살이 많은 고기예요
So let's let's bring this up and we are going to have to change the scale.
이걸 불러와서 스케일을 바꿔야 해요
We're going to have to come down.
우리가 내려가야 해요
There we go.
됐어요
Now you can see everything.
이제 다 보여요
If I leave it at one.
1시에 끝낼게요
Okay, so a few things to point out.
몇 가지 짚고 넘어갈게요
So first of all you're seeing a purple.
우선 보라색이 보이죠
Let me click.
클릭해 볼게요
I think if I do this one here it's going to bring it up.
이걸 누르면 위로 올라갈 거예요
There we go.
됐어요
So you can see here a blue and a purple line.
파란색과 보라색 선이 보이시죠
The blue is just here and the purple is here.
파란색은 여기쯤이고 보라색은 여기예요
The blue is the current run that is running right now over on this tab.
파란색은 현재 이 탭에서 실행 중인 실행이고요
It's this this guy that we are running right at the moment.
지금 우리가 실행 중인 이 남자요
The purple is the one that I kicked off a while ago.
보라색은 제가 예전에 버린 거예요
I of course it has the data in there about ten days ago.
물론 10일 전에 데이터가 들어있죠
Um, and you can see that the blue is tracking extremely closely to the purple, which is further evidence
보시다시피 파란색이 보라색과 아주 가깝게 붙어 있죠 제가 속임수를
that I'm not I'm not cheating here.
쓰지 않는다는 증거예요
Uh, it is the case that that blue will continue to follow the same trajectory as the purple.
저 파란색은 보라색과 같은 궤도를 계속 따를 거예요
The purple has just had its course.
보라색은 이제 다 됐어요
Uh, now, what you'll see is that the trend indeed improves and improves and improves, which is good
보시면 아시겠지만 경향이 계속 발전하고 있어요 좋은
Ish.
거죠
Um, so first of all, you'll, you'll see that it that it improves and then it takes a little dive
우선, 호전되는 걸 보실 거예요 호전되고 또 호전되고
and then it improves, and then it takes a little dive again and improves and it takes an even bigger
또 호전되고 또 호전되고 더 호전되죠
And so you might be wondering what are these dives?
이 다이빙이 뭔지 궁금하실 거예요
Well, these dives are the end of each of the epochs.
이런 잠수로 각 시대의 종말이 온 거죠
So this is an entire epoch.
한 시대의 이야기죠
That's epoch one, that's epoch two, that's epoch three, and this is epoch four.
1번 시대를 거쳐 2번, 3번, 4번까지 반복될 수 있죠
And unfortunately it crashed.
불행히도 추락했죠
Uh, or Google reset the instance uh, halfway through uh, epoch four.
구글에서 이포크 4 중간쯤에 인스턴스를 리셋했어요
So, uh, we didn't get to see how epoch four ended.
Get it 에포크 4가 어떻게 끝났는지는 못 봤네요
Um, but as you'll see, that that proves to be unimportant.
하지만 그건 중요하지 않아요
Um, so why does the why is there this sudden drop at the end of each epoch?
왜 각 시대 말에는 갑자기 폭락하는 걸까요?
Well, that's a very good question.
아주 좋은 질문이에요
It's extremely important.
아주 중요해요
Uh, it's because what's starting to happen is a little bit of overfitting.
비트가 좀 과하게 들어가 있어서 그래요
What's happening here is that the model is seeing some of the same data that it already saw in the first
이 모델은 첫 이포크에서 본 것과 같은 데이터를 보고 있어요
Now, sure, it's muddled up differently.
물론 좀 뒤죽박죽이긴 하죠
and seeing them in, uh, in batch batches that are different sets of 16 than the ones that got here.
16개씩 다른 세트로 묶어서 파는 걸 봤어요
Hugging face takes care of that for you.
얼굴만 안아주면 돼요
The SFT trainer automatically reshuffles the batches each time.
특수 훈련 담당자가 자동으로 배열을 바꿔요
Um, but nonetheless, the models had the benefit of seeing this data before, and it can take advantage
그럼에도 불구하고 모델은 이 데이터를 전에 본 적이 있고 그걸 이용할 수 있어요
It's learned something despite the dropout.
중퇴했지만 배운 게 있어요
Um, despite some some other things we've done to try and regularize, um, it's still has a leg up
정규화하려고 여러 시도를 했지만 여전히 이런 데이터를 본 적이
on the fact that it's seen this exact data before.
있다는 게 문제예요
Um, but luckily there's only a small step down there, so we don't need to be too concerned that there's
다행히도 작은 계단만 있어서 너무 꽉 끼는 건 걱정
overfitting happening.
안 해도 돼요
But then it gets worse here and it gets significantly worse here.
하지만 여기서부터 훨씬 더 나빠져요
Uh, and so this is a big sign of overfitting.
너무 꽉 끼어서 그래요
And now, if I had been doing what I told you is a best practice and I should have been doing, which
만약 제가 말씀드린 최선의 관행을 따랐다면 즉, 유효성
was running validation runs at the same time, uh, the chances, first of all, they wouldn't have
검증을 동시에 실행했다면 성공률은 이런 점프 다운을 하지
taken these little jump downs.
않았을 거예요
But secondly, it would have probably started to go up at this point because we're overfitting.
둘째, 지금쯤이면 가격이 올라갔을 거예요 너무 많이 들어갔거든요
And indeed I have savings of the batch at this point.
그리고 지금은 저축해둔 게 있어요
And sure enough, it was saved up to the Hugging face hub every 5000 steps so I could test it.
아니나 다를까 안는 얼굴 허브에 저장되어 있었습니다 5천 걸음마다 테스트할 수 있도록 말이죠
And sure enough, the results do get worse past the third epoch, so there was no point in going more
세 번째 시대 이후에도 결과는 더 나빠졌으니 세 번 이상은 시도할 필요가 없었죠. Get
than three epochs.
it!
So it didn't matter that Google pulled the plug on my instance at this point, because this data was
구글이 이 시점에서 제 인스턴스를 중단한 건 중요하지 않아요 이 데이터는 더 이상
actually no longer useful.
쓸모없으니까요
The model was already doing poorly.
모델은 이미 형편없었어요
And again, this is a great example of where you can regularly upload to the hub, and then you can
이건 훌륭한 예입니다 허브에 정기적으로 업로드 한 다음 각각의 체크포인트로
go back at each of these checkpoints and run your test over them.
돌아가 테스트를 실행할 수 있죠
And you can pick the model that performs the best.
가장 잘 어울리는 모델을 고를 수 있어요
And that's a very powerful technique for so that you don't have to guess how many epochs to run.
아주 강력한 기술이라 몇 개 시대를 개혁할지 추측할 필요가 없어요
You just run too many and then select the one that has the best results out of your training data.
너무 많이 실행한 다음 훈련 데이터에서 가장 좋은 결과를 얻은 걸 선택하는 거죠
Out of sample when you're trying something new.
새로운 걸 시도할 때 샘플이 다 떨어지죠
Um, so I think it's a really good illustration of of how this works.
이게 어떻게 작동하는지 잘 보여주는 예라고 생각해요
Um, and of the, the, the, the effect of overfitting and the effect of different epochs.
과잉 착용의 영향과 다양한 시대의 영향도 봤죠
And, but what we know for sure is that during that first epoch, say, because it was always seeing
하지만 확실한 건 첫 번째 시대를 맞이한 이후 새로운 데이터가 끊임없이
new data, all of this slope downwards is all representing good improvement.
쏟아져 나왔다는 겁니다 이렇게 기울어진 건 모두 개선의 징후예요
And I can tell you that the results at the end of here were also distinctly better than here.
여기 끝부분의 결과도 여기보다 훨씬 더 좋았어요
So this was also showing some improvement.
이것도 발전을 보였어요
And but around here it started to get a little bit more dodgy.
그런데 비트 박스가 좀 더 위험해졌어요 get it get it
And maybe, maybe coincidentally that is at around the 1.5 level.
우연의 일치로 1시쯤에 찍은 것 같아요 5층요
And I mentioned before there was that rule of thumb that less than 1.5 maybe is a time to be raising
아까 경험 법칙이 있다고 말씀드렸죠 1보다 less요 5점이면 눈썹을 치켜들고
an eyebrow and looking again at your results.
결과를 다시 볼 때예요
Uh, so I will pause at this moment, and when we return, we'll talk a little bit more about a couple
이 시점에서 잠시 비트를 멈출게요 다시 돌아오면 몇 가지 다른 것에 대해 좀 더
of other things.
얘기해 보죠